you
the central theorem of Markov chain is
called a good exterior have you heard
this expression before
ergo the theorem if you haven't I'm
going to tell you what it is it turns
out I'm going to say this slightly
loosely but you understand that for
every initial distribution however you
start a Markov chain this chain this
Markov chain if you keep going for long
enough converges to a limit the switch
over thank you village and to a linear
distribution and this limit distribution
in fact is unique and this limited
distribution is often called by
physicists statistical equilibrium
that's for example the equilibrium state
you get in statistical physics
stationary distribution in nature and so
the stationary distribution is
absolutely correct in the theory of
Markov chains if you know that world so
much the better
I didn't write it because people seem to
understand it a little better but
station is efficient and swim as time
goes to evening we shall prove this
wonderful a parabolic theorem rather
easily and the reason the proof is easy
although the result is beepin useful is
thanks to the power of proposal of
thinking in terms of pictures I should
say that there are many different
versions variable in serum this is not
the only one I stated the one that is
clearest but there are many others that
you might encounter strategy scientific
area and some of them need techniques
from outside topology but this one this
simple one can be completely understood
in terms of propulsion another comment
that I shall make before starting the
proof another comment I said it
converges to a limit distribution in
other words if you keep iterating very
soon you see some distribution say two
thousand rabbits here three thousand
rabbits here 100 rabbits here
only one rabbit here and 20 hundred and
twenty thousand rabbits here and so on
such that when you keep applying the
Markov chain
it doesn't change that's why as Sheamus
said it's a stationary distribution is a
linear distribution okay so it's a
distribution of probabilities
probability distribution that no longer
evolves you have reached an equilibrium
the temperature has settled and so it
doesn't have to be a uniform
distribution you get a uniform
distribution if all the generality
the same but otherwise this country have
more probably here less poverty here so
but you get a limit distribution
now it's a bit annoying to have a
mathematician saying it converges to a
limit because natural scientists we
scientists want to know how fast it
converges and as a Christian says oh
when n goes T goes thinking it converges
but we want to know for example when T's
100 has it already more or less
converged maybe it's not going to be
exactly limit but maybe it's very close
to it oh maybe after 100 steps were
still very far away we don't know
however although I won't be I will not
be able to explain this that convergence
is extremely fast it does so for all
intents and purposes
after several steps you can assume that
your state is roughly in equilibrium
that's why the world most of the world
we see is in equilibrium much over the
time as soon as we go away from a cream
very quickly you come back to the food
after all the speech let through this
result the key remark is the one that we
have been using in exercises yesterday
and the day before the limit
distribution is a fixed point of this
mapping G
why is this you see if you look at this
formula it's also true that p1 at T plus
1 and p.m. at T plus 1 is equal to G
applied to T 1 T 2 T M T correct so
click the minute on both sides as T goes
to infinity what do you get
well you get the equation that the
limiting distribution at time infinity
is equal to G applied to the same
distribution which shows exactly that
when you apply this distribution vector
does not move so the limiting
distribution limit which will be shown
is a fixed quantity and you can see how
the browser expansion can be applied so
the problem then is to prove the
existence of a fixed point
in Danvers because jesus H X what does
this say it says remember geez mate ryx
and biometrics it says that this vector
is an eigenvector you see because if I
apply this matrix this vector becomes
proportional to itself but the VA it's
an eigenvector but what's the eigenvalue
so here what it becomes 1 times itself
so or to find prove the existence of an
eigenvector with eigenvalue 1 there is
something else though it's not enough to
find an eigenvector with eigenvalue 1
for example suppose that you found the
eigenvector which looks like this 1
minus 2 and minus 0.1 suppose that this
eigenvector has eigen value 1 that's not
what we want because all those entries
are probabilities they cannot be
negative
furthermore dimmers are not 1 so that's
not so you want an eigenvector who's
such that each P I is positive 4 or I
and the sum of the three RS is one with
eigenvalue 1 that's what we want you see
it has a local constraints but those
constraints the constraints will be over
advantage to us
you might have been watching carefully
and might have noticed that I'm cheating
a little I said the problem is to find
an eigen value or a fixed point in fact
you should also prove that this
convergence takes place you see the way
I presented argument says that if it
converges then the limiting distribution
is the I is again vector and so forth
but I haven't quite said why this
converges I will skip this step with
apologies it is not difficult and if you
are interested I'll be able to I will
show you but that step is purely
analytical you have to write some
inequalities and you see that the
convergence takes place and you more of
a see an idea remembers that the
convergence is very fast I'll stick that
step because it's not related to
topology and I'd like to show you focus
on the topological part diagram which is
the existence of one fixed point of the
eigenvector probabilistic eigenvector
with eigenvalue 1 right the statements
this existence has a name
the existence of an eigenvector like
this with eigenvalue 1 this thing I'm
sorry about right right here is called
pebble Frobenius theorem which has quite
a lot of applications in Applied
Sciences to people they won't proved it
in 1907 Frobenius who has a great
professor saying they'll be improved
1912 and for some reason both people
would have pre-credit
that's very nice you proved something
five years after somebody else on
YouTube yet remember but in general you
should be aware that in mathematics and
in science when you see some results
called after somebody you know for
example something is called Brownian
motion well it probably was not
discovered by mr. Broun usually the name
of a result is not that of a discoverer
of the discovery it's probably somebody
else and history is complicated so this
principle that the result in science in
mathematics in particular is almost
never named after its true discoverer is
called Tadashi's principle
because he was not discovered by I hope
you use this Prince principle to
advantage
let's then discuss and establish the
existence of an eigenvector of G with
all positive entries and such that they
adapt one whose eigenvalues as the DA
points out is one no 30 again we are
going to essentially draw a picture the
space of all probability distributions
which I'll write it like this P 1 2 p.m.
you see that the probability of being in
state 1 to state 2 and so on and this
simply is a vector in RN such that as we
wrote 3i is open space for all I and the
sum of the entries is one such a space
can be drawn as a picture
wonderful is you might call a
tetrahedron or generalized in Trujillo
by which I mean a shape like this but
please realize that I'm mean the shape
with a solid interior also how do I mean
that of different dimension M minus 1
here is how let's do it in the case N
equals 2 that only two states so P 1 and
P 2
those are axes and I'm drawing only the
first quadrant this part and not the
rest of the plane because P 1 and P 2
must be positive
both of both of them greater than zero
and they must adapt one so what does the
picture of p1 plus p2 equal one look
like I hope you can draw this in one
second it looks like this that's 0
that's 1 that's 1 if you are anywhere on
this yellow line it is the case that P 1
plus P 2 is 1 this summons 1 and each of
these is greater than equal to 0 ok now
that doesn't look really like turkey
drawn or a triangle but watch next case
M equals 3 P 1 P 2 and P 3 I hope he has
seen the picture that I'm seeing I'm
looking at the corner over over room ok
in this space this part the octant with
puppets sticking up to us you has the
property that all the peas are positive
in this octant what does this set this
set look like I hope you can draw this
set in 2 seconds it looks like this you
take a point on the P 1 axis at distance
1 from the origin P to access a distance
R from the origin and III axis at
distance 1 from the origin and you
connect those three points that gives
you a triangle which is put into a
corner not all the way to the corner but
sort of put in a corner and this
triangle is exactly the shape that's
represented there P 1 plus P 2 plus P 3
cos 0 is equal to 1 now it looks like a
triangle right this is if you like a
one-dimensional triangle that's a
two-dimensional triangle yes and in
higher dimensions
triangles are coated
he drones in dimension three you know
what it looks like I hope that's exactly
the picture I drew before it has four
vertices and then you connect them and
they say interior it looks like this
it's difficult to imagine this perhaps
because we cannot draw the picture still
over four dimensional space and see what
he said P 1 plus P 2 plus P 3 plus P 4
equals 1 looks like but it looks like
this essentially that's why I call them
tetrahedron and it's between quotation
marks because it's not quite at receiver
and tetra means 4 faces so it's not
really for but in dimension n minus 1 is
the same what is very important is that
G acts on this tetrahedron in any
dimension and this tetrahedron is
homeomorphic to a ball of dimension M -
mark
why is this let's check that it's
homomorphic to be minus one for example
is it true that this yellow thing is
remembered to be of 3-1 what is P of 2-1
it's B of one yes what's the one
dimensional ball hey it's a segment is a
line between minus 1 and 1 so you see
it's homomorphic topologically the same
shape next let's check the statement in
dimension 3 Direction 3 let's peel 3
minus 1 it's b2q dimension about what is
two dimensional ball look like it's cold
it's cold at least yeah disk does it
look like this well yes it's a
disc you have mr. one has coolness but
it doesn't matter
it's a disc to polish them and so on so
of dimension n minus 1 what does it mean
to act it means the following let's say
that I start from for example somewhere
here so p1 is something T 2 is something
and then I apply this matrix G in this
case 2 by 2 matrix and that gives me P 1
and P 2 at the next moment in half but
the mean p1 and p2 must still stay on
this line yes because it's a probability
distribution so all it's doing is that I
move this point to maybe somewhere else
and each point on this line moves to
some other point on this time
similarly here let's say that you have a
case Markov chain with three states
where in this stage and suppose that PU
the state one has a probability p1 state
to provide EP 2 step 3
being probabilities P 3 so we are
somewhere on this planet at time 0
what's gonna be the probability
distribution at time 1 well I apply this
G to the vector p1 p2 p3 and
I get a new vendor okay that new vector
is the probability distribution at time
one but that means that I still have to
stay on this triangle so I have a map
from this planet of God itself a special
map that the optional G similarly in a
dimension G is mapping this tetrahedron
or to be precise this set to itself all
the time Oh Wallace so G takes this set
and Maps it itself but this step is
homomorphic to a bowl so brava applies
and says that there must be a fixed
point and automatically this fixed point
satisfies the constraints because we are
applying fixed point theorem in this set
let's take maybe two or three minutes in
order to see examples of how this works
and then you might see this argument and
the picture a little later
consider a Markov chain with only three
states so this phenomenon this universe
this system can be in one of the three
states state let's call it state 1 let's
go to state 2 let's call this state ok
for some reason I'm writing 2 1 3 I I
don't know why I'm writing this in this
order and then we shall assign how they
jump let's say that if I'm state 1 I
always stay at state 1 so I jump from
state 1 to state 1 we will probably see
one I don't go anywhere else let's also
say that if I misstated to I moved to
state 1 with probability 1 and if I
mistake at stage 3 I moved to state 1
with property one in other words this is
really a deterministic process you
understand at each moment of time I show
what to do next
there is no probabilistic uncertainty I
just know now suppose that you start
from some probability distribution and
then I run this Markov chain what do you
think will happen after one step what
happens all the rabbits which were
distributed in state 1 step 2 step 3
what happens to them they also jump to
state 1 and stay there forever so that's
the limiting distribution limit the
distribution is well at any later time
if you look at this system after you run
the Markov chain you are sure to find
everyone in state 1 in other words the
state is instead
with property one and you can never find
a state in privity in state Tuesday
three okay so the limited distribution
if you think over the back that p1 p2 p3
should be P 1 is 1 and P 2 is real 0 1 0
0 that should be the limit distribution
right let's see if that's really the
case in this case what is G well
remember this is this is a probably fee
that one just 1 so it's 1
what was this probability here
tip 1 so 2 jumps to 1 and that's 1 and 3
times 1 that's 1 here is probably that
one jumps to 2 which is 0 2 times 2
which is 0 and it's 0 0 0 ed can you
calculate the square of this matrix the
cube of this matrix G x GD x GD x GD x
with Angie can you calculate this well
in principle you can but let's note that
1 0 0 is a fixed point
is that true huh if I apply this to 1
0-0
what do you get 1 0 0 so it doesn't move
and it turns out to be the only fixed
point and we check please fill the check
if you're worried if you are not worried
I'm not a mystic please trust me that G
square is simply equal to G itself and
similarly for any P not equal to 0 G is
just G so
for any ol initial distribution t1 and
t2 and t3 the three of them - we have
that the limit of G super T of P 1 0 P 2
0 3 0 so this is the probability
distribution time T is simply equal to G
single power because you know for
anything it's equal G of T 1 0 into 0 is
race alone and if you remember what
chimp lady looks like it's very easy to
see it is equal to what's the first
component if I apply this G to this
victim without the visa and
hard-of-hearing it's not like before you
do the calculation what happens if I
yeah that's like p1 0 plus P 2 0 plus P
3 0 yes and house where you get to 0 and
0 but what is this term is of course 1
because you know I am talking about
probabilities so this is equal to 1 0 0
so you see that the fixed point is the
limited distribution the limit is the
fixed point so this is what
let us discuss another example which is
only slightly more complicated but not
so trained and this is elastic
example 19 let's now discuss a system
with only two states state 1 state 2
okay and will not make it
deterministic and Bob will make it
probably stick let's say that state 1
jumps to stay tuned with the property
3/4 okay and state 2 jumps the state 1
with poverty 1/3 in that case the chemo
arrows here 2 goes to stay tuned and
spectral goes to state 1 what is the
probability assigned to this our
workforce because this and this must
account for the possibilities and here
is 2/3 easy enough let's cause that is
Markov chain the transition or the
generator matrix simply looks like this
and this is 3/4 I mean I think ok you
might have noticed that if you take the
generator and add each column each
column adds up to one and that's because
we are talking about probabilities
excellent
what is a fixed point of this matrix
it's not easy to see how about maybe the
fixed point is not easy to see but you
can find out by calculation certainly
right what you're doing is you apply
this to P 1 P 2 and it should be equal
to P 1 P 2 you have two equations two
we can certainly find what P 1 and P 2
are effectively at the calculation you
are doing is exactly the same
calculation as the one for finding
eigenvectors and eigenvalues you must
have done such calculations up enough
number of times in your undergraduate
days when you learn linear algebra
matrix theorem so well this is the kind
of problem where it's used it actually
has a meaning and I did this situation
at home and if I'm not mistaking for 13
and 9 13 is a fixed
and you can trust me your life is short
so it's mine but I devoted some of my
life to make your life more you but now
I do have one comment about this to say
that it's a fixed amount means that if I
apply G this factor becomes itself but
money I take twice this vector what's
going to happen if I apply G well it's
going to be twice this vector - yes so
that's also a fixed point that's also a
fixed point and so on yes
in particular for nine that's a fixed
point of this matrix why it's one rather
than this one exactly because those are
supposed to be probabilities it's nice
that I find a fixed point with positive
entries but also the entries must adapt
one that's why I divided by thirteen so
what happened when I did the calculation
was I found this first but I said oh we
have normalized make them probably so
divided by something okay anyway that's
a fixed point
therefore we know from the general
theory Markov chains and Theory theorem
particulate we proved that for every
initial distribution even zero that the
limit as time goes to the future of G
key of this applied to the same initial
distribution so this is the probability
of being States one or two at time T
must converge to 430
amazingly no do you understand what this
is saying it's saying that whatever
initial vector I choose for example if I
choose the vector 1 0 that is the
simplest and then 1 0 1 0 I keep this up
- matrix over and over and over again -
1 0 quickly I converge to this vector
yeah that's it and see if I start from
any other thing 0 1 I apply this over
and over again you conversely to this
vector what Shane is commenting is that
there are different kinds of Markov
chains but regular Markov chain and
irreducible component and so forth
that's the interesting part I mean the
other words that non-reducible irregular
and so on but those words I introduced
in order to think about uninteresting
cases in some sense so that's the heart
of the that's the simplest but difficult
part of the theory and once we
understand it the rest is just language
ok the theory of Markov chains as I
explained is very central phylidia as
you might have guessed probabilistic
thinking especially thinking in terms of
stochastic Arana processes is very very
useful in modern sciences I hope you
like it and I hope you appreciated
topology times its use even in areas